so today I'm joined by Jonathan Paige Oh
a lot of people say hello Jonathan so we
can see your face
hello everybody right I guess a lot of
people watching this will know who you
are already
you you've done quite a few public
events with Jordan Pederson already and
yeah you actually reached out to me to
to talk about the value of organized
religion and it's something I don't have
any sort of firm views on so it'd be
really interesting subject to explore
but I'd love to to start by talking
about the the recent Sam Harris Jordan
Peterson debates because I know you've
been quite vocal about your view of of
how those have gone and whether they've
actually achieved anything and given
that they're sort of fairly recent I
think that would be a good place to
start and then move on to about personal
histories with Christianity the value of
organized religion and then sort of
maybe unpacking a few of these questions
around the kind of ambivalence of Jordan
Peterson's reawakening or re
understanding of some of the Christian
tradition and then that relation to the
organized church and whether yeah that I
sort of sent some tensions there that
I'm fine I'm kind of interested to
explore yeah yeah first of all thanks
for for agreeing to talk with me I've
been kind of following the videos on on
and off you know I I saw the first video
I remember what I saw your first video
your first day with Jordan then I kind
of I kind of had a little negative
reaction to your to your video but then
I've been following the your discussion
and I saw the video with Paul and I've
been seeing kind of your interpretation
of things and I felt like you you really
do have a this kind of desire to enter
into the discussion and to to figure out
what's happening maybe like just what is
going on cuz obviously something is
happening and there aren't that many
people trying to to figure out what the
the size of this thing that's happening
and kind of what the ramifications and
so I really appreciated your your desire
to kind of take it on and engage and so
I thought it would be great to to have
a direct discussion with you so thanks
for having me thank you
just I remember what that was it was the
Gnosticism line we've got I'd love to
explore my friend and colleague Ali is
an expert on Gnosticism or researched it
quite a lot for a free book so I won't
call him an expert but he researched
quite a lot so he'd love to have a
conversation with you at some point
about Gnosticism I know yeah sure I
would look I would love to do that too
like I think I'm for sure it's it is it
is for sure I do have a Christian
perspective on Gnosticism and sometimes
the let's say the Christian perspective
on narcissism is polemical that's for
sure
and so so I kind of understand that and
so I would be happy to to talk with
somebody who studied it more and and and
kind of Duke it out and have that
discussion that it'd be great to do that
great cool yeah you've said a few really
insight exciting things there that I
want to just question I mean you you
talked about this thing that's happening
and I think there's a lot of I mean what
I sense on a sort of broad scale is
there is a kind of intellectual
awakening facilitated by the internet
and the kind of the new media the
ability to go down as many rabbit holes
as we want yeah but how would you
summarize it I think so I think it's I
think what's going on I think there's
also something that's going on it's that
we've kind of reached the end of a
certain cycle or we reach the end of a
certain time where we kind of moved into
a kind of nihilism you know in terms of
everybody all they wanted was to you
know to have the nice car and to have
you know a kind of superficial
superficiality and we saw that in in the
news and in the way that we've been fed
media for the past you know 10 20 years
where you know we've been told how our
attention span is shrinking and you know
we need to have these 10-minute bits and
then advertisements and and so we can
see it on TV still like it still has
that model where they they have these
little short tidbits of things that they
present you and then they kind of move
from one thing to the next and I think
that what we're seeing is is we've just
reached the end of that because that's
just not true that that's what human
beings are we're just not we're not like
that and so it's actually pushing us in
a direct you know it can it's like you
could say something like everyone
likes to eat chocolate cake and if you
give someone chocolate cake like they'll
love it
obviously they'll want to have more but
if you eat chocolate cake for two days
at some point you just get totally
saturated and you want to have some
veggies and I think that's where we are
is that they've the the the media
companies thought that they could just
give us this candy forever
but at some point people just got
completely fed up and now they want
they're looking for something a bit
deeper and a bit more intense and
they're not getting it from the
universities for anybody who studied in
university it's so ideological
especially the humanities it's so
ideological there's so little room for
actual engagement in actual discussion
actual plunging into the text of Western
history that people are looking for it
on the Internet and luckily we have some
interesting people that are kind of
coming up I think and I think that
Jordan Pederson has been someone who's
kind of filled fill that a place but
there are some people they don't have
the big as much following is Jordan but
you'll find philosophers online that
have you know fifty thousand followers
and their view their there their
lectures have you know fifty thousand
views on this like obtuse concept in
Heidegger or like you know reading Hegel
and it's like they have fifty thousand
views which is just insane it means that
people are really hungry for something
more than just the just the Kardashians
you know yeah yeah and do you do you tie
the the Sam Harris Jordan Peterson
debates in any way to that sort of the
changing of world views or the changing
of different perspectives because I mean
Harris is obviously the sort of the
foremost advocate for the materialist
paradigm which I at least would sort of
say is partly what has led to the kind
of the sense of a lack of felt meaning
in people lives yeah I mean there's a
great line that sorry I'll just okay
there's a great line of a friend of mine
came up with recently which was he said
scientism is worse than jihadism because
jihadism doesn't create you
weapons yeah exactly that's yeah there
is a kind of I think that it's
interesting to see it kind of from the
outside is to see in a lot of the this
kind of New Atheists bunch a kind of
blindness and in a kind of certainty
which you actually do discover in in
Jobos witnesses for example you know
like this kind of absolute certainty of
what they're doing and also a pros like
a like a proselytizing where they just
kind of want to convince you of their of
their thing and so it's really funny -
it's funny - guys it's funny to see that
but it is kind of frightening to think
like you said that behind behind you
hope as witnesses all you have are
really annoying conversations at the
door but behind behind scientism you
have artificial intelligence you have
all these things like the the the trans
human is for example I mean they're it's
frightening how they're not they don't
have wisdom to to kind of understand the
the propositions that they're making
this idea of putting you know let's say
electronic devices in the brain to
increase people's thinking and time
Eris's for actually is for some of that
stuff and and so it's like they they
don't seem to understand the basic the
basic wisdom of humanity that how that
would be problematic they don't seem to
be able to see what that is um but I
think it's interesting it's been really
interesting at first you know when
Jordan was trying to kind of engage with
Sam Harris I didn't totally understand
why he was he was so adamant about doing
so because Jordan really did want to
have this discussion with him um I was
actually at Jordan's house at the second
discussion that Jordan had with Sam
Harris you know the first one was the
horrible when the two-hour like train
wreck the second one wasn't so bad and I
was actually at his house and we we went
over like the first time Ayers debate
with his son and and Jordan we watched
we like we like listened to the whole
thing then we kind of analyzed it where
did it go wrong and everything so Jordan
was really is really adamant about Sam
and I kept wondering why him like why
him and I think I know what it is I
think I think because there is something
in Sam Harris which represents a
beginning of a transition it's there in
him because of all the new atheist types
he he has had spiritual experiences now
and he can't discount them like he can't
pretend like those are meaningless he
knows how meaningful they are and and
because of that he he does have a desire
to recover something of spiritual
tradition it's just that he still has
like it's like he's kind of has a one
foot in two worlds and he's trying to
figure it out it's as if Jordan also has
his foot in two worlds right Jordan
isn't totally on the religious side or
on the scientific side it's just that so
they both have their foot in two worlds
it's just that maybe one is pulling more
on one side and the other is kind of
pulling more on the other when it's
saying there is value there's more value
than you think in the religious aspect
and the other is saying there's very
little value in the religious thing the
only thing that's that's worthy is the
discussions about consciousness and and
you know especially Eastern or mystical
experiences like that's all that matters
and so I think that that's why I think
that that's why the discussion has been
so engaging for people people have been
so wanting to to follow it because I
think people are trying to figure that
out they're trying to to understand how
because every I think most people do
have an intuitive sense that there's
more like there's any to ative sense
that there's something about our being
in the world which has meaning which is
and you have to actually work really
hard to to destroy that to just be a and
most people who do that they they
actually are deluding themselves cuz
they say that they're just monkeys you
know and they're they're just a bunch of
monkeys who are saying things but but if
you if you pay attention just a little
while to what they're saying you realize
that it's not true they have hierarchies
of values they have they have spirits to
which they pray they don't even know
that they're praying to to certain God
but they're there at the altar of
certain gods and they're there there
there there
sometimes even possessed by those
spirits you know and so so I know that's
why I think it's been so interesting for
people to to follow this because I think
that's the discussion that people want
to hear now because we it's like we have
we're in a moment where we have a loss
of meaning we everybody's experiencing
it like there's a there's a kind of
chaos of meaning a chaos of identity a
sense that things are crumbling or
things or we're not
anymore together we live in our little
suburban homes we don't know our
neighbors we don't have community we
don't so so all that is is real and
people are looking for solutions to that
in the discussion between Jordan Sam is
taking people just like one little step
at a time towards figuring out what that
means even in terms of translating it in
a way that people who are kind of
scientifically minded could understand
hmm yeah I do you have a sense of could
I guess both of us share a sense that we
think Peterson has a bigger perspective
on this than Sam Harris and how do you
sense that those debates have gone I
mean and do you have a sense of what
would need to shift for Sam to
appreciate for example the fact that
values have to be have to be rooted in a
story for example I'd say the
fundamental disagreements between them
must pretty much that are they that
values have to be they can't be derived
rationally and they have to actually be
more deep-rooted than that yeah I think
that it's funny because at the end of
the London discussion its Sam who
started to talk about consciousness it's
like towards the end of the discussion
and I felt like ah this is the place
this is the spot where the discussion
the next step of the discussion needs to
happen the thing is that Jordan Jordan
is Jordan doesn't hasn't studied a lot
let's say in terms of Eastern tradition
terms of in terms of Buddhism and also
even in terms of Christianity he hasn't
studied the mystical tradition so much
and so the idea of not just having a
spiritual vision let's say but actually
elevating your consciousness as we say
or transforming your consciousness to to
become more to be freer to be to be less
bound by our multiplicities less bound
by our passions all that stuff that is
in the mystical tradition I think that
that's the key for Sam that's the that's
the discussion that is going to help him
break break his
way that he sees some of some of this
stuff like what I would like to have
like if I had a discussion with Sam
Harris I would just say okay look I know
you don't like religion yeah I'm
religious that's fine let's not talk
about that cuz gonna be a dead end let's
talk about consciousness let's talk
about that and let's lay it out okay
what does a world in which consciousness
is central how does it lay itself out
how does attention lay itself out
right it laid itself out in terms of
hierarchies terms of higher kids you
have a point of attention and then
around that point lay the world kind of
flows out into chaos which is on the
edge even in your visual frame that's
how it worked right so you have points
of attention and then on the edges you
have this chaotic space which is which
is kind of gray and not totally there so
you say okay so now let's take that
experience of consciousness and let's
say that that's the foundation of
reality that's what he says he says
that's the foundation of reality well is
there an analog to that in a community
what does that look like what does a
commute what does the analog of
consciousness in a community look like
it looks like it looks like gathering
together around a point
looks like turning around appointed it
sits circumambulation it's a it's a it's
it's a hierarchy of social of structure
and it ends up looking like a religious
ritual that's what it looks like right
because that's that's religious rituals
are have the same structure as the
structure of consciousness so I think
that that and then how does what does
that look like in time what does the
experience of consciousness to look like
if you see it with the frame of time and
what it looks like is a story it's the
same and so I think that that's that
would be the work that I think could
kind of help Sam Harris move a little
bit further down down the road I don't
know he's he's actually also his whole
world is his whole career his everything
about him is caught up in his in his
position and so you I don't know I don't
know if he'd be willing to make that
move I thought the debates themselves
were very frustrating I thought they
were useful in the sense that I thought
that Jordan had a chance to say what he
wanted to say and I think that people in
the audience people are going to be
listening to it some of them are going
to be rolling
make the work to do the work some of the
some of the schemes that he laid out
like the scheme of human sacrifice I
thought was like if you're if you're
honest and you and you're honestly
attentive to what he's saying you will
see how strong what he's laying out is
and how evolutionary correct like in
terms of just evolutionary thinking how
correct what he's laying out is and so I
think that some of the viewers will
probably be willing to make the work I
don't know but for Sam
I think consciousness India I don't know
I think he was gonna do a an interview
with Don Hoffman I don't know if he did
it but I think that someone like Don
Hoffman could help Sam kind of move
forward like Don Hoffman I don't know if
you know about about him did you follow
that
what you're talking about is that is the
phenomenology of consciousness yeah
you're sort of basically saying this is
the way that you get you you try and
argue some heresy the phenomenology of
consciousness what does it look like
because that's what he says that's what
he says is the basis of reality and the
thing is that the phenomenology of
consciousness doesn't actually transfer
easily into scientific thinking it's
actually scientific thinking is actually
quite far from phenomenological
consciousness phenomenological conscious
actually looks way more like a very
primitive vision of the world where
there's up there's down you know and
your whole experience is there to tell
you when you're up and down because when
your head is upside down you don't feel
right you know you don't feel right and
so that your whole body and your whole
experience is there to experience heaven
and earth and is there to experience
time and is there to experience also
limited attention and then a hierarchy
of attention and and that's how we set
up our communities everything set up
that way so I would kind of move through
that with him to to get him to
understand what these stories are about
so yeah so that's that's kind of that's
what we're trying to that's what I'm
trying to do like my brother mature he
wrote a book on cosmic symbolism in
Genesis and that's exactly what he's
trying to do he's trying to bring it
back to consciousness and show you how
the structures in in Genesis the stories
are basically that's what they're
talking about you know the story in
Genesis the creation story it's obvious
that that's what it's talking about at
least in part I mean you
have the use of word you have this
notion of
opening your eyes and then being self
aware and and then actually covering
yourself to protect yourself from the
outer world it's like the whole story of
the fall
it's obviously talking about
consciousness it evens that's what it is
it's a sum it's a being who who acquires
a certain type of consciousness and then
the effects of that consciousness on
that being I don't see how you can't see
it it's obvious that's quit it's about
anyways yeah it's I think you also spoke
to that it's it's very hard once someone
has established a position written a lot
of books on a certain perspective to to
go through an experience of having to
change their minds I think that's that's
a that's a big part of it but I think I
think that it it's not it's not I think
it's not impossible in a way Sam Sam is
also someone who is who is honest he has
these paths he has these weird patterns
that he falls into you know and it's
like Jordan Jordan was talking about I
mean he laid out this amazing discussion
about this this notion of of a mimetic
process by which we identify the ideal
man the ideal human and then we project
this ideal human and we represent him in
the dome of a church into heaven right
of of your experience and then we look
up together towards that mimetic
representation and then we see it as the
model by which we live our lives and
then sam harris is like yeah but what
about finding out fundamentalists it's
like that's all he could say was what
about fundamentalist what about it's
like you're not this discussion is not
moving forward it's not in it you could
do this with anything you could do that
with anything and I love when Jordan
said do it take stories do it do it with
the Hindu stories please Sam do it if
you say that you can do it with anything
do it maybe it'll give you some insight
into into how these stories work and how
this stuff works and it's not that it's
not all arbitrary and it and it's not
just a bunch of stories we tell each
other you you can't escape even if you
enter into an evolutionary way of
thinking you can't escape it everything
you do
to be within that so our stories have to
be part of it our concepts have to be
part of it everything has to be part of
it
you can't just discount an aspect of
humanity as if it doesn't matter because
that means you're not trying to
understand what it means what it is to
be human can't just say it's silly well
you have to be able to it's there you
have to be able to talk about it because
that's also part of of the yeah let's
say the the emergent phenomena like you
have to be able to talk about it yeah
and it also speaks to that paradox that
the Peterson points out about you can
either be an evolutionary thinker or you
can be an atheist who doesn't see how
those two things fit together or you
have to admit that religion has some
something this long-lasting and powerful
must have some evolutionary benefit yeah
and also the idea that for example that
we want to discount irrationality that
we want to be rational it's like okay
well then you're not taking into account
the fact that we're irrational I mean we
are obviously irrational to like it's
it's obvious that we are and so they're
much there are reasons there are
purposes for our irrationality it's not
like irrationality contains the entire
scope of human experience so if you want
to say that that you can only filter the
world to rationality then you're you're
definitely creating something which is
going to be lopsided and and what I
think and what Jordan thinks is that
it's going to create a totalitarian
result because you're you're unaware
like you're totally unaware of what of
what the that other aspect of ourselves
is so yeah so it's it's a very it's a
very strange yeah
this is something I've heard I think in
the in those debates Sam calling what
what Jordan believes dangerous quite a
few times I maybe I haven't heard enough
Viktor does Jordan describe what Harris
believes are dangerous as well or is it
kind of a one-sided discussion on that
on that front I think that I think that
it's interesting because I think Jordan
I think it's will Sam's retort to
- Jordan is that you know all the the
horrors of the 20th century and let's
say the late 19th and early 20th century
those were still religious so religious
thinking that we're continuing you know
and and I think that that's where Jordan
kind of he once in a while he'll give
like a like a thing okay talk about Mao
and Stalin and then Sandra toward his no
that's still religion and I think that
Jordan hasn't totally figured out a way
to to kind of move past that without
starting to argue and he doesn't I don't
think he wants wants to argue but I
think that that's and because it's Sammy
was so funny the way he dealt with that
in that discussion where Jordan brought
that up and Sam said I'm gonna deal with
this cuz I'm sick of hearing this
argument like I'm sick of hearing it and
I'm gonna deal with it once and for all
then he said something like it's he said
what you would expect no that's still
religion but it's like I'm not convinced
my buddy I'm not convinced at all
because it was already there in the
French Revolution you know all that was
already there in the French Revolution
in a smaller scale but we're talking
we're now we're talking about tens of
thousands and maybe up to a few hundred
thousand people that were slaughtered
because of reason like they they clearly
said that that that the motivating
factor behind their action was reason
science progress that's exactly what
they said and they even had the cult of
Reason where they they destroyed all the
the church they would empty out the
churches and they used the church
building to celebrate reason and so they
would all get together and celebrate
reason and and and that happened in the
blood of the peasants like that have
been soaking in in in Catholic blood so
I think that I think that I think that
that's kind of a it's a frustrating
thing and I think that's I also actually
also think that's what makes sense
position dangerous is because he thinks
that he is innocent he thinks that he's
innocent and that his position is only
innocent he always says something like
atheism just means the belief in no God
there is no positive aspect to to
atheism now we want to propose after
that let's leave that aside and we want
to propose some positive things and he's
in the position where he can say well
what I propose has never been tried it
doesn't exist and so hi it's so
beautiful look at how beautiful what I'm
proposing is and he doesn't he can't he
can't underst
and the side effects of what she's
proposing can't understand how when you
do something you cannot you don't
necessarily know the ramifications on
the side and so he complains I'd say
about about North American nihilism and
their obsession with their cars and with
celebrities but then he somehow sees
that it is negative but then he wants a
secular society it's like well maybe a
secular society gives that because
that's what happened and the other
alternative to that too like the kind of
mall going fat you know diabetes like
maybe the only opposite to that is to
anchor yourself in something like reason
or nation or something lower on the the
hierarchy and then becoming a yeah
becoming an ideologue and and then just
going and destroying churches or you
know killing whatever group that is
going to be killed because he's not part
of your thing so anyways I like I said
I've said this in the describe before I
don't think Sam Harris is the one who'd
go out and and burn churches obviously
not it would be more like the FARC type
you know like Varg would you would take
the atheism to go in and destroy
churches it wouldn't be Sam but in the
wake of what he's proposing that's what
those are that's what's gonna happen
I like I can't see anything besides that